so our next speaker is Donald Robinson
Donald is cbt trained psychotherapist
and he's the author of six books on
stoicism and I mentioned this before
Donald is really the the super glue of
the whole stoic community I don't think
we'd be here today if it wasn't for him
and and the efforts and initiatives that
he took to organize the stoicism
internationally and he released the
recently released a book called how to
think like a Roman Emperor and today's
talk is how to practice like an old
Roman Emperor and so we're going to is
going to examine Marcus releases
meditation and what kind of spiritual
life practices can be gleaned from it so
let's give a warm welcome to Donald
Robinson thank you very much
okay hi everyone so I did quite a formal
exercise with you and you've done a lot
of meditation today which is really cool
so you'll already be pretty mellow and
contemplative earlier we had some
discussion our theory before we did the
view from above and now we're going to
do some kind of discussion of strategies
and concepts after having done a an
exercise that's going to be interesting
as well and I'm going to go through a
whole bunch of psychological exercises
that I found in ancient stores Azzam so
my background is in cognitive behavioral
therapy and the niche that I've kind of
ended up finding my cell phone is
talking about the the psychological
practices that are found in store sysm
so I'm going to go through a whole bunch
of them and give you some hints and tips
about how to actually put them in
practice and because these are
techniques I've been using in workshops
and with clients and therapy and
coaching for about 20 years know why
that was how this whole thing got
started I was saying earlier you you saw
a picture of the first workshop that we
did the Exeter University and I was in
that group I don't know if you spotted
me in the photograph my hair was a
little bit dark : there's a lot better
less wrinkled and that whole idea
started because of an audio recording of
the view from above the same exercise
that you guys did earlier and that went
online and some students at Exeter
listened to it and they thought we
should do this thing called stoic weak
and that was how this whole thing got
started basically but I'm going to throw
in some stories as well and anecdotes to
make that sizes a little bit more
interesting so we'll see how that goes
and the story I wanted to start with is
about Socrates actually because I I
believe the I read the Stoics as being
Socratic s-- I can I think it's very
important it's very valuable to look at
the Socratic dialogues or Plato and
perhaps see more so the ones from
Xenophon in order to put the Stuart
ratings and exercises in context and a
lot of the things that we found in the
Stoics can be found
teased earlier in Socrates often with
more supporting arguments
and Plato's Republic I think him book
four and then this is returned to again
at book ten I'm speaking from memory so
I if I remember rightly some of these
references should be as I described but
you guys can fact check them later
Socrates is talking to glow cone Plato's
brother about the Greek tragedies and
glowkies said Socrates what do you think
of the tragedies are really cool aren't
they you know wait when Oedipus goes
crazy why because he finds that he slept
with his mother and Medea goes crazy
because she finds her husband Jason
sudden affair and she kills her children
and stuff it's like we've got some
awesome tragedies and this is a high
point of Greek culture and Socrates
surprisingly shockingly says well yeah
but I don't think these people have
really good role models in fact their
case studies in psychopathology why
maybe that's what they would be good for
and then in and he says the wise man
wouldn't respond in the face of
adversity in this way and then in book
ten he returns celebrate honor and go
out Khan says well hello then Socrates
would a wise man respond in the face of
adversity
and Socrates says well he would do four
things first of all he would tell
himself the the it's never clear when
something happens whether it's
ultimately good or bad and there are two
reasons for that like in the tragedies
there are many reversals of fortune in
life somebody may lose their job maybe
the best thing that ever happens to them
our relationship may break up seems like
a terrible catastrophe at the time maybe
it's for the best in the long run yeah
so things that seem like a catastrophe
is may in the long run turn out to be in
our best interests and the other reason
is the someone might lose their job like
one person make court badly whether
another person may clown from the
experience so it depends on the use that
we make of these experiences so it's not
clear whether something's actually going
to be good for us or bad for us so we
should kind of suspend judgment and not
be unduly alarmed
we encounter what seems like a
misfortune and Glenn says that's
interesting Socrates well the other
things that wise man does in the face of
adversity as Socrates says well the
other thing is a cell it tells himself
it's unnecessary to add another layer of
suffering to something that may already
be painful and unpleasant why would you
make yourself even more upset why would
you make yourself suffer even more when
the situation that you're already facing
is painful difficult and unpleasant
quiet keep another layer of suffering on
top of what's already happening make a
bad situation worse and Lacan says well
what was the thought thing Socrates and
Socrates said well the wise man tells
himself that nothing is that important
and the grand scheme of things so for
either piece like finding out that he
slept with his mother is like the most
awful thing that he can conceivably
imagine Medea finding out that Jason's
betrayed her is as terrible like the
worst thing that's conceivable to her
now Socrates says but you know like none
of these things are actually that bad
like nothing's that bad in the grand
scheme of things and to the philosopher
oh that's more obvious because he looks
at the bigger picture he takes the long
view he looks at things within a broader
context and when we look at things from
a broader context nothing is that
extremely awful as we see in rational
emotive behavior therapy it's
authorizing our catastrophizing
exaggerating the severity of the
situation
and quite Cohen said but he said there
are four things Socrates was the fourth
thing that the wise man tells himself
and Socrates says well the fourth things
are most important of all Glaucon he
said the wise man tells himself that if
he's like either purse or Medea and it
gets really angry and really worked up
like he experiences and indulges and
they're rational passions then he's
doing precisely the thing that's most
unhelpful in the face of a crisis he's
preventing himself from doing what's
actually required in the face of
adversity which is thinking clearly and
rationally and solving the problem that
he faces because when we indulge in
irrational emotions as the stoic said
it's a form of temporary madness and it
prevents us from being able
- thank clearly about the situation
we're facing and solve it rationally so
those are four strategies that Socrates
mentions more concisely than not he
mentions a number very often can a
fleeting way in Plato's Republic and
that's a pretty stoic right why we can
see echoes of those sort of ideas in the
in the stoic literature as well but I
don't know would we call those exercises
or not one when we talk about techniques
or practices in therapy people have
different ideas about what would
constitute a psychological exercise so I
would call those cognitive strategies
those are perspectives or ways of
interpreting the situation maybe even
sentences or coping statements that
someone might use in the face of
specific situations so as a therapist my
trainer
I would conceive of those as
psychological exercises and there are
also other types of psychological
exercises that we find in cognitive
therapy and in stoicism that may involve
particular lines of questioning that may
involve visualizing situations or
adopting certain alternate perspectives
on a situation such as the view from
above that we looked at earlier and when
I roll my first book on stoicism which
has just come out in a second edition it
was originally published in 2010 and
it's called the philosophy of cognitive
behavioral therapy it was kind of
intended for a dual audience of
philosophers and professional
psychotherapist it wasn't meant to be a
kind of self-help guide although a lot
of people have read it for that reason
and what I was trying to do is to make
sense in my own mind of the relationship
between stoicism and psychotherapy and
part of what I did in the book was to
try to list all of the psychological
strategies that I could find described
in the stoic literature so I did a
survey of all the relevant literature I
could find and all the commentaries that
I could find and I tried to list and
itemized the main psychological
practices that I could find and there's
different ways that you could carve
those techniques up so some of them can
be lumped together more in groups or
some of them can be broken down into
different forms and we could divide them
into general psychological strategies
which may take the form of multiple
specific types of
Niek so give you some examples of that
as we're talking but overall the last I
drew of distinct psychological
strategies in that book I hadn't
numbered them I went back recently
encountered them they were 18 right so
there's a whole bunch and armament on
armamentarium is a term that used to be
used in psychotherapy and made this in
the toolbox we might say of stoic
techniques it's quite broad and so you
may ask well are some of them more
important than others and I think they
are why there are some that cannot stand
though or that list to explore emphasis
on all that seem like they would be more
foundational basis not clear-cut answer
to that question because often they seem
to intersect and overlap with each other
so I'm keeping an open mind about that
you know and I'd be interested in what
your thoughts about that are where some
of them do seem to be more important
than others in Marcus Aurelius for
example at one point in the meditations
tries to provide a summary of what he's
doing in that book so there are several
places where he summarizes the
strategies he's using and meditations
1118 he talks about techniques for anger
management and he lists 10 distinct
psychological strategies they're all
positive strategies for coping with
anger
I think that's impressive if I asked an
audience of cognitive therapists to off
the top of their head less ten distinct
psychological strategies for coping with
anger I think they've come up with five
or six maybe by he can last ten and we
can tell he knows them very thoroughly
and deeply he keeps returning to them
throughout the meditations but in
another passage he says look basically
all of the Spoils down to two basic
ideas and he sums them up concisely in a
short phrase in Greek it's only six
words it's very brief laconic so stoic
slight to compress things so that they
can be easily memorized and they were
ready to hand in the face of adversity
like a coping statement or Maxima or an
affirmation and therapy today
he says the universe is change life is
opinion and luckily we know who he meant
by that because in the preceding passage
he can have a library it's honor a
little birth and it's a beautiful little
concise expression of the store so some
of the meditations anyway but
he happens to be clearly referring to
two philosophers and the the two
philosophers he say it's most frequently
throughout that lat Burke the universe's
changes the reference to Heraclitus like
the pre-socratic philosopher who Marcus
refers to almost as often as Epictetus
his favorite philosopher and the second
part life is opinion is a clear
reference to epictetus I'll come back to
that in a moment and elaborate on it
just as an aside John earlier I've
talked about the idea of illusion and
the view from above and perspective
shifting as a as a way of dealing with
the illusion and life and the cynics in
Stoics actually have a word for illusion
the cynics called it 2/4 and the the the
Stoics sometimes used this word as well
it means smoke or mest like a smoke
screen or like smoke and mirrors and the
senate said were surrounded by to force
all the time in the world and marcus
aurelius and another famous passage i
believe it's the last passage I can't
remember which number has but in book 2
of the meditations he says life is a
sojourn and a foreign land
life is warfare and a sojourn in a
foreign land and he says everything to
do with the body
is like a flowing river and everything
to do with the mind is like a mess or a
vapor to force like the passions a kind
of smokescreen an illusion so these are
two fundamental parts of this philosophy
that he keeps returning to and looking
at the world in terms of these two
concepts is aching a foundational
psychological practice that Marcus
employees and many of the other
techniques visualization techniques
verbal techniques he refers to cane of
relate and somewhere another back to
these two basic concepts and one of them
relates to our experience of external
things the nature of the world that is
constantly changing I you can't step
into the same river twice like
Heraclitus said and when Marcus says
life is change he means everything's
constantly in flux
it also means when we look at the bigger
picture when we expand our perspective
we see that the present moment is just
one small
of the patroness transient and life this
change also means that life is death I
mean is that when we think about the
transience of things we have to come to
terms with our own mortality and
contemplating our own mortality as you
probably know is one of the major themes
of stoicism and of the meditations as
well
so that's kind of being eluded to him
directly and not short phrase and life
is opinion means that the quality of our
life is shaped by our judgments
particularly our value judgments
according to the Stoics and I'll come
back to that because it's one of the
most important concepts and stoicism so
here are some of the practices that I
like to go through cognitive behavioral
therapy I'll speak more to that in a
moment as influenced by Stewarts ism but
not a lot of people know this that was
actually an earlier attempt to integrate
stoicism and Western psychotherapy
nothing to do with Freud and
psychodynamic or psychoanalytic therapy
at the beginning of the 20th century
there was a rival to Freud about a guy
called Paul Dubois who was a Swiss
psychotherapist and a neurologist and
Jabbar really liked Seneca and tried to
assimilate Senecas flaw he would
prescribe reading letters of Seneca to
his patients and he developed a form of
psychotherapy called rational
psychotherapy or persuasion
psychotherapy is that sometimes known
that was first time competed with
Freudian psychoanalysis and was
influenced by stoicism but the better
stoicism that Dubois and his colleagues
emphasized is slightly different from
the bet that came to be emphasized later
what they emphasized was the bet that we
call today the dichotomy of control so
the dichotomy of control is the
distinction between what's up toss and
what doesn't and I like to frame as
being a distinction between what we do
and what merely happens to us and life
it's the distinction between reports
under our voluntary control and
everything else
or as Epictetus Spitzer what's up to us
and our world are our own actions our
voluntary actions and that's
distinguished in stoicism are demarcated
from everything else
it's famously encapsulated in the
serenity prayer
give me the serenity to accept the
things I cannot change
the courage to change the things I can
and the wisdom to know the difference so
this is a kind of obvious psychological
strategy and it was integral to early
20th century rational psychotherapy but
not so much emphasized and modern
cognitive behavioral therapy although
there are some things that can of
resemble it and I'll just give you a
couple of quick examples that's the
thing that we do often in cognitive
therapy where somebody excessively
blames themselves for a situation and I
used to work with road traffic accident
RTA victims and they often were
traumatized and blamed themselves for
accidents that they've been on and so of
very often I would ask them to draw
maybe a pie chart and to split up in
segments what factors were to blame for
the accident or I'd ask them from zero
to 100% how much control did you have so
I begin by saying look from zero to
percent how much do you feel as if
you're to blame for what happened and
they'd usually say a hundred percent or
ninety five percent or something like
that and then I'd say let's ever think
about it
way you know rationally speaking from
zero to hundred percent how much control
did you actually have over the outcome
and they might say five percent are
often zero percent certain I'd say voila
why how is it possible why that you can
be a hundred percent to blame but zero
percent in control surely these things
don't really make sense they by side
yeah so getting them to realize that
they've been taking too much
responsibility for things that aren't
actually under their control is an
obvious and integral part of that type
of therapy but really it has much more
pervasive value than that would imply
another technique that you can employ a
very simple way of doing that would be
just to draw two columns
describing a situation you're facing and
in one column less the situations that
you're worried the aspects of the
situation that you're worried about and
then the other column less the aspects
that are actually under your direct
control and just kind of sorting through
our parsing things and that way and can
often be tremendously helpful this takes
a lot of time and reflection and so the
idea is closely related to another story
he called the reserve clause that has to
do with undertaking action so stoic say
that whenever we undertake any action we
should also always do so with the caveat
I will do such and such fate permitting
or I will do such and such if nothing
prevents me acknowledging that the
intention to achieve some goal and the
actions that we take from moment to
moment are under our control but the
eventual outcome might not be so it
entails distinguishing between what's up
to us and what what is not a famous
example of that is in Lukens for salia
an epic poem that describes the the
Roman Civil War and that was written by
Senecas nephew who was also a stoic we
have most of its surviving today I think
we're missing one chapter and in the far
salia Cato who is organizing the
remnants the Republican Army to fight
against Caesar I was marching through
the desert and one of his officers finds
a shrine to Zeus and they say we wish
you'd consult the same to find out what
the outcome of the battle is going to be
that was a very common thing for Roman
generals to do they wanted to consult a
shy and get prophesy about who would win
the battle and Cato in the force alia
and this kind of really epic fragment
says no I don't need to for a start I
don't believe that God lives in a shrine
all that have to speak to him through
priests because I'm a stoic I'm a
pantheist I believe that God is
everywhere and everything that I need to
know he's already implanted and saved my
heart so I have no need to consult a
shrine and Cato also says it doesn't
matter whether we win or lose I've
already accepted the possibility that we
might lose the forthcoming battle either
way I'm gonna do the same thing if the
shrine tells me we're going to win I'm
gonna fight Caesar if the Train tells me
I'm going to lose I'm still gonna fight
Caesar because it's the right thing to
do
we're opposing a dictatorship so the
reserve Clause Kenneth Cato says I'm
going to undertake this action and the
service of my moral principles while
accepting that we might feel or we may
succeed that's not under my direct
control in cicero's de finibus he
describes a famous metaphor what she
puts in the mouth of Keitel and he says
think of it like an arch
or a Spearman so imagine someone's
throwing a spear at target and I think
this example works better if you imagine
the target is an animal and the Spearman
is hunting so he can throw the spear to
the best of his ability and he'll aim at
the target the wild boar that he's
hunting let's see but he can't control
if it suddenly darts off in the opposite
direction he might mess it so all that
he can do is what's under his ability
under his control to the best of his
ability and then he has to accept the
outcome whether it's success or failure
and that's sportsman like if you like
he's just doing his best and not
grumbling if he's unlucky in the hunt
for instance and that idea is related to
something that we can also call stoic
acceptance so Epictetus
regarding the reserve clause says it's
like saying I want to do such-and-such
and at the same time keep my volition my
will in harmony with nature by accepting
the outcome even if it doesn't go my way
Epictetus also famously said do not seek
for things to turn out as you desire but
wish for them to be as you as they are
and your life will go smoothly so this
is a kind of form of rational acceptance
and the Stoics don't mean I cannot
passivity by that they mean trying your
best to do what's wise and just in life
but accepting the reality of your
situation would be a better way of
putting it being brutally honest with
yourself and not grumbling unnecessarily
about things but accepting what happens
this idea of stoic acceptance cane of
his in some ways and inheritance from
the cynic concept of voluntary hardship
which actually reminds me a little bit
of the breathing exercise that we just
did because in modern cognitive
behavioral therapy and third wave
therapy we often teach clients to endure
our voluntary discomfort and that might
be through holding their breath for
example and one way one reason for doing
that is to teach clients a tolerance of
uncomfortable or unpleasant sensations
some people are much more intolerant of
those things than others and that can
often cause some problems in life it can
cause some emotional psychological
problems but you can train yourself to
become more accepting of discomfort and
Marcus Aurelius rightly says in
meditations if you do that with one
feeling you should also tell yourself
the other feelings are just the same
they're all these bodily sensations so
if you hold your breath and can come to
terms with the discomfort of that you
can learn to view it as just a sensation
you can do the same thing when you're at
the dentist and tell yourself it's just
the same as when I was holding breath
it's just a different sort of bodily
sensation or all these bodily sensations
he says fatigue illness why they're all
the same like the stoic response is
basically saying that just bodily
sensations and we can employ similar
strategies to cope with them so when
we're training those skills on a
specific sensation we should think of
them as generalizable in other words
Marcus says to himself when enduring an
uncomfortable sensation he literally
says is this unbearable like he's
challenging himself this sensation when
taken in isolation is it really
unbearable people tend to say I can't
handle it it's too much it's unbearable
so he challenges himself to question
whether this moment alone is really that
overwhelming is it really too much for
me because we can tolerate we can bear
most of these things if we take them one
step at a time and small slices so this
idea also cannot leads us on to the
concept of premeditation premeditation
malorum which I like to call the
premeditation of adversity William
Irving calls a negative visualization
but I don't really like that term
because the thing that the stoic is
visualizing isn't framed as negative in
fact it would be more like indifference
visualization the idea for stoic says
that we should confront situations that
seem like misfortune like death exile
poverty other setbacks in life and train
ourselves to view them with stoic
indifference to accept the discomfort
the awkwardness of them and to
can i raid that Oh like to realize that
these things aren't necessarily the end
of the world to employ some of the
cognitive strategies that our honor I
mentioned Socrates talking about
so the Stoics cannot do two things when
the undertaking a specific action will
in advance
Petra that it may turn out badly for
them and rehearse coping with that like
an example a key tool leading the
Republican Army against Julius Caesar
but also Vil Petra or Seneca often
mentions a variety of different
misfortunes that may be unlikely to
actually happen to them in practice and
we get the same distinction in modern
therapy and what we call imaginal
exposure training so we can get clients
to cope with specific challenges that
they face maybe they're going to have
surgery and they're anxious about it by
picturing that specific situation as
vividly and realistically as possible
and rehearsing that in the controlled
manner in specific ways in the mind but
also to build a more general form of
psychological resilience we know that
what helps is not to focus on one
challenge but on a wide variety of
different situations and we can see
Seneca talking about that and the
letters Tillis Elias and elsewhere for
me the most important stoic technique
though is the one that's mentioned in
enchiridion five and one of the reasons
that's particularly prominent for me is
that it is that for that particular
passage and the enchiridion was used by
Albert Ellis the founder of rational
emotive behavior therapy way back in the
1950s one of the pioneers of modern CBT
and he taught this quote to every client
the quote that goes it's not things that
upset us but our judgments about things
that's what upsets us and that's what
Marcus is alluding to when he says life
is opinion that it's not things that
upset us but our opinions about things
that encapsulates what we call today the
cognitive model of emotion and that's
the basic premise of all cognitive
therapy so Ellis found an easy way to
teach that to clients in therapy was
just assure them that quote from
Epictetus and that's one of the reasons
there's a kind of
historical intersection between stoicism
and modern cognitive behavioral therapy
although I have to say most modern
cognitive behavioral therapists that may
be all they know about the Stoics that
just that one core unfortunately
although they would benefit I think from
reading more about stoicism in many
cases they'll know that quote from
Epictetus but maybe literally nothing
else about stoicism but it's an
important core it is fundamental to
stoicism I call it cognitive distancing
our cognitive catharsis and it's
mentioned in the Socratic dialogues of
Plato and also in dialogues Xenophon and
so I would I like to thank it make all
the way back to Socrates himself and
actually Epictetus seems to know that he
hints at her because in the next
sentence his example is Socrates he says
if death were inherently awful and
fearsome then Socrates would have been
frightened of dying but he wasn't there
for like the anxiety the terror that
people feel towards death must come from
their attitude towards her and so one of
the ways that we illustrate the
subjectivity of these emotions the fact
that they come from our value judgments
projected onto things is by asking
ourselves that other people feel
differently about the same situation and
that's an age-old strategy we find that
in Xenophon and Plato as well and the
mouths of Socrates if other people
aren't upset by the situation if they
feel differently about it then maybe
it's not the situation that's upsetting
you maybe it's your attitude towards it
there are many good examples of this and
the Socratic dialogues I think one of my
favorites is in book 1 of the Republic
which many people believe presents a
more authentic picture of Socrates and
was maybe written earlier by Plato and
then it's Socrates visits a well thief
elderly man he's friends with a foreign
immigrant in Athens called careful us
and care forces as an old man in
Socrates hasn't seen him for a number of
years and he says what careful is like
just as if I was embarking on a journey
and I met somebody that was returning I
might ask them what's the territory like
ahead but what's that things am I gonna
encounter
on the rest of my journey because you've
been ahead of me
like you're ahead of me in life like
because you're older than me by several
decades what's it like being unable to
layperson and carefully says to him well
I hang around with a lot of other old
guys because birds of a feather like to
flock together and the one thing I
notice about them is they like to
complain by Dawn so what that tells me
is whether it's good or bad isn't a
matter of the aches and pains or the
health problems or other limitations
that go with old age itself but I
believe it's more down to their attitude
that you have towards earth because if
it was inherently awful then everyone
would feel the same way about it and
some people are happy in old age there
are positive aspects to it and he
mentioned some and he says I've got more
leisure time to talk with my friends and
so on for example no he says I view it
in a more positive way so like I think
it's really the attitude that you bring
to it and he also says as an aside I
don't think these guys have ever been
happy to be honest and now they're even
more unhappy and oh they were
complaining when they were young and now
they're complaining when they're old
because I think if you approach it with
the right attitude though then you know
it doesn't have to be a negative
experience it's all in your attitude he
says so it's not surprising the
epictetus then uses Socrates as an
example because he had this idea of
cognitive distancing but this concept is
has become very prominent in therapy
because more at least recently the third
wave researchers and CBT Beck argued the
phone one of the phone does a cognitive
therapy argued look and cognitive
therapy we get clients to question the
evidence for the beliefs that are
upsetting them so somebody says nobody
likes me everybody hates me I think
we'll go and eat worms and the therapist
will say where's the evidence foreign
against that belief that nobody likes
you and you may get them to evaluate
that but Beck says there's a
prerequisite for that before you can
even get started doing cognitive
reappraisal you have to get the client
to treat that belief as if it was a
hypothesis why if they just think I'm
just describing what I see it's a fact
that everybody hates me then I'm not
going to be in a position to start
weighing up the evidence for and against
it's unquestionable they just think
they're describing something that they
can see right in front of them
they have to separate that belief from
their external experience and realize
something that they are imposing on
events it's an interpretation an
attitude it's something they're
projecting before they can begin
evaluating they have to treat it as a
hypothesis recognize it as a belief
rather than fusing it with external
reality and so this tendency to fuse
things with external reality as seen now
is a fundamental problem in much
psychopathology it's a central focus a
modern thought wave psychotherapy and
the Stoics were way ahead of their time
and clearly highlighting this problem
Marcos phrases it definitely throughout
the meditations he talks over and over
again about separating his mind from
external events separating his value
judgments from external events life is
opinion is all about the interpretation
that you impose on things
why so you have to realize that you are
imposing an interpretation because we
tend to forget that we confuse our
opinion with reality and so the first
step of cognitive therapy in the first
episode system is realizing that we're
doing that and actually what the food
we've therapists found was that when you
do that rigorously enough you don't even
have to start disputing the evidence for
a foreign against in many cases they
realize that once you gain in cognitive
distance those negative beliefs become
less evocative and less disturbing so
they thought what happens if we just
train people in Dustin Singh Steven
Hayes the founder of acceptance and
commitment therapy did research on that
fender of act and he called the
comprehensive distancing he said what
happens if you just did that but we
thought it was preparation for therapy
but maybe it could be the whole therapy
and they found that that works about as
well and in some cases maybe even better
than disputing the evidence for negative
beliefs and it's a lot simpler because
there's kind of only one thing know that
you need to do and actress Epps has also
realized that this I didn't come from
Buddhism but it's similar to things that
happen in meditation so when you're
meditating and thoughts pass through
your mind you have to gain a certain
amount a distance from them not to be
sucked into them and drawn along with
them
so this kind of attitude of mindfulness
and detachment became very important in
modern therapy and thoughtwe therapists
started to draw on Buddhism but
ironically they could have looked at the
Stoics less mindfulness which the Stoics
called pro so he continually being aware
of the way that we're projecting our
beliefs onto external events that our
tendency to fuse or thoughts with
reality prising those apart constantly
being aware of that is integral change
in stoicism but it was one aspect of
stoicism the back and Ellis ignored why
when they developed what we call second
wave or perrolli cognitive behavioral
therapy and there it was reintroduced
under the influence of Buddhism so I
like to encourage modern coated paper
therapists to realize that there are
mindfulness practices already in the
stoic literature that complement the
this passage from enchiridion five so I
think I'll wrap things up there because
really I wanted to just give you a
sample of some of some of the the stoic
techniques that I think are most
important and and talk a little bit
about the practical application give you
a few anecdotes and then I was hoping to
kind of throw open to questions and and
see if I can because you guys been
meditating today so I reckon that your
questions are going to be really cool
and I like to do Q&A so what we throw
open for Q&A now if you guys already do
we have
[Music]
so I think we will have time for three
or four questions it's anyone in the
audience have a burning one right off
the bat for Donald great thank you so
much for the talk the exercise you were
mentioning at the end of the distancing
he reminded me of just the skeptic
therapeutic program and I was wondering
if you could elaborate a bit perhaps on
your opinion on the downside to that
because I think the Stoics would
disagree that just doing that is healthy
they would think we should do the second
step and I guess I want in your opinion
on on that the Stoics can't talk about
suspension or judgment and the same way
as a skeptics but I suppose what the
story could say is that we shouldn't do
that in relation to virtue they think we
can grasp the nature of the good of the
nature of virtue with certainty and so
Marcus actually talks about that in some
cases he says he talks about applying a
similar technique and he says apply this
to everything in life except virtue I
and I should mention one of my favorite
techniques I'll just mention in passing
and act clients are taught to take a
problematic statement that maybe
encapsulates the judgment and to say it
really quickly for one minute so you
might say everybody hates me everybody
hates me everybody hates me everybody
hates me hates me everybody hates
anybody it's me hates but everything
hates me hates me hates me hates me
everybody hates TM becomes really
awkward very quickly but it makes you
much more aware of it as an activity it
becomes cumbersome so you become more
aware of the awkwardness and the fact
that you're actively engaging in the
thought you take more ownership for
because you've made or caused in your
medium or yourself more self-conscious
over that creates cognitive distancing
and it tends to make people then feel
that the thought is less distressing it
seems kind of arbitrary to them they go
well I could say that to myself but I
don't have to it's like something not
them it's a habit I've gotten to and I
could just stop seeing up
thank you so much for your talk Donald I
actually a question that I guess kind of
builds off of that but you talk a little
bit about how comparing act versus CVT
you said there's like interesting
evidence and different populations who
benefit more from not cognitively
challenging every single thought as
opposed to this like radical acceptance
kind of piece and how you you've seen
some benefit and I just I would love to
hear your thoughts on like what kind of
people benefit more from that or like
what the rationale is for someone
benefiting less from constantly
cognitively like challenging each
thought and like evidence for evidence
guys versus just to like the radical
acceptance in what you're and when
you've seen that work the research or
not the stell emerging research or not
but the short answer to is that most CBT
practitioners will say the clients with
generalized anxiety disorder or certain
obsessive compulsive clients sometimes
find it difficult to do traditional CBT
because I mean to put it very glibly and
just give you an example and CBT you
give a client a flop form a take home
and you go right down what Forte's went
through your mind and then in this
little column jot down the evidence for
and against and some of the GED clients
have generalized anxiety disorder which
is called it's basically pathological
worrying they'll come back for the next
session and go you told me it write
stuff down so I've written ten pages
well in thoughts went through my mind
you go okay no you're like massively
overthinking it
right so for them the process of
thinking becomes sticky because they're
so fused with her why and so the
desperate ation itself becomes something
that they become to a milestone why and
so we need to can I'll teach them to be
able to take a step back from that and
not get swept away by their thoughts as
much and you know it doesn't necessarily
correspond to particular diagnosis you
know although some are more problematic
than others maybe you just be certain
personality types aren't really suited
to disputation because they they get too
lost in the weeds basically and
sometimes it's helpful to do something
that that's less discursive
it's just a question on the is the sort
of the spirituality side of it how much
for you is it stoicism and she be purely
a technique to overcome psychological
issues and how much of it is there is
there a spiritual religious element to
stoicism well I'm an agnostic right but
I got into all of this stuff because as
a teenager I was interested in Buddhism
and world religions and Nakata long
story short it was studying Christianity
that led me to Neoplatonism that led me
to stoicism violin or Styx basically so
that's that was my background bringing
me into him when I was at university
studying philosophy I also studied
history of religions
I studied I studied Buddhism and
Hinduism so I I do kind of have that
perspective but over the years I've got
more into Greek philosophy I guess in a
sense my outlook has become secularized
although I guess in a sense that's
telling me I do I find it hard to kind
of draw the line as to you know what
would qualify as mysticism Bertrand
Russell that says maybe this is an
indirect way of answering your question
Bertrand Russell who was famously an
atheist said that he considered studying
the whole of human history and an
overview the closest that he could
imagine to a religious experience and
that reminds me of the view from above
so I think the view from above even if I
approach and I can a secular rational
way cane a quasi mystical experience
perhaps and some people tell me they say
Donald you're a mystic because you rent
all this kind of stuff and I think what
I offer really view it that way then I
think maybe we're just kind of mincing
words or whatever so if you want to call
that kind of mystical or a spiritual
aspect then I guess I'm good with our
although I tend to think of it more as
philosophy and our rational way of
viewing things we don't yeah cool okay
thank you very much
[Applause]